[Music]
a randomized controlled trial of
hundreds of pregnant women found that
having women eat around six dates a day
for a few weeks before giving birth can
significantly improve cervical ripening
the the readiness of the cervix the
opening to the birth canal you can also
use drugs or surgery to prep the cervix
oxytocin is the most common agent
you may have heard doctors talking about
pitocin that's the brand name although
it's effective its use is associated
with multiple potential adverse side
effects which can affect both the mom
and the baby
if only there were a safe simple side
effect free solution well
dates may fit the bill
the use of oxytocin for labor induction
in the date group was less than half
that of the control group and the few on
dates that were induced had more
successful deliveries
an earlier study in which prior day
consumption appeared to shorten labor by
more than six hours speculated that
maybe dates themselves have
oxytocin-like effects
all right how about a head-to-head trial
comparing the efficacy of dates versus
oxytocin
in the management of postpartum bleeding
postpartum hemorrhage excessive blood
loss after birth
is one of the major complications of
pregnancy and the leading cause of
maternal mortality
as the placenta peels off the uterus
it's supposed to contract to stop the
bleeding
and if it doesn't if the uterus doesn't
have sufficient muscle tone
you can give an injection of oxytocin to
help squeeze off the blood loss
like all drugs though can have side
effects sometimes causing a dangerous
drop in blood pressure
there's also various devices that can be
inserted to apply pressure and worse
comes to worst surgery
but why not try fruit first available
cheap side effect free yeah but does it
work
they set up a randomized clinical trial
to find out
immediately after the placenta comes out
women were given a one-time dose of like
five dates or an intramuscular shot of
oxytocin and then they just collected
all the blood to see which worked better
overall
three hours after delivery the blood
loss average in the date group was
significantly less than in the oxytocin
group by about a quarter of a cup
check this out see how the date group
was mostly in the lowest category under
two-thirds of a cup of blood loss
whereas the drug group was mostly about
a cup or more conclusions
use of oral dates i don't know how else
you take them after delivery decreased
bleeding more than intramuscular
oxytocin and it's a good alternative in
normal delivery but wait if dates have
oxytocin-like effects to contract the
uterus shortening labor by helping to
induce earlier uterine contractions
might date consumption increase the risk
of premature labor
i guess we'll never know until
now
the effect of date fruit consumption on
the length of gestation
starting at about 38 weeks women were
randomized to eat seven dates a day or
not
and
eating dates did not affect delivery
dates
but what it did do is significantly
reduce the need to hasten labor with
drugs half of the non-date group had to
be drugged versus 30 percent less than
the seven dates a day for a week group
an induction of labor is serious
business it can increase complications
such as bleeding c-sections
uterine hyperstimulation and even uterus
rupture
and apart from the complications women
who are induced tend to feel less
satisfied with their birth experience
therefore
date consumption in late pregnancy is a
safe supplement to be considered as it
reduced the need for labor intervention
without any adverse effect
on mother and child
the only thing we're missing now is a
double-blind study not just a randomized
trial but a placebo-controlled
study right i mean the women in the date
group obviously knew they were eating
dates
and maybe that had some kind of placebo
effect
the only double blind study i could find
on dates and delivery is in arabic but
the english abstract describes how women
just entering their active labor phase
we're given a date syrup or placebo
that's brilliant right hard to make a
placebo date but you could make some
kind of placebo syrup like molasses or
something right
no when they say honey date syrup
they're not talking about a syrup of
honey and dates but a syrup made out of
honey dates which is a soft melt in your
mouth variety easy to whip into a syrup
and normal labor progression was
evidently higher in the date group
around 98
compared to less than 70 in both the
placebo and control groups and labor
duration was also shorter in the date
group like two hours shorter so on your
due date maybe we should give dates
there do
[Music]
you